A Guide to the Clarke Family Papers, 1854-1890
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Clarke Family Papers, 1854-1890
Library of Virginia
22095
70 items (180 leaves).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Lent for copying by J.G. Hamilton, 10 March 1943.
Biographical/Historical Information
Colin Clarke (12 September 1792-17 October 1865) was born at "Keswick" in Powhatan County, Virginia. He graduated from the College of William and Mary in 1811 and later served on the school's board of visitors. He represented Powhatan County in the House of Delegates from 1816 to 1819, and Chesterfield County, Virginia, from 1826 to 1828. Clarke married Mary Goode Lyle (25 October 1801-22 December 1884) of Chesterfield County on 16 April 1818. They had nine children, all but two of whom survived to adulthood. In 1834, Clarke purchased "Warner Hall" in Gloucester County, Virginia, and moved his family there. One daughter, Sally Bland Clarke (b. 1828) married John Laurence Manning (1816-1889) who became governor of South Carolina.
Maxwell Troax Clarke (10 June 1830-21 December 1911) attended the University of Virginia and became a merchant in Richmond, Virginia. He served in the Confederate navy during the Civil War. He served under William Francis Lynch (1801-1865) in the sounds of North Carolina and as a commander in the James River Squadron. After the war, he returned to his business and also served as a justice of the peace for Richmond. He married Ellen Scott (27 March 1830-2 June 1908) 2 June 1857 and they had 4 children. Colin Douglas Clarke (22 May 1832-10 April 1862), a farmer before the war, served in the quartermaster's department, becoming a major. He married Elizabeth Berkeley Cooke (1 November 1833-4 February 1906) and they had 4 children. John Lyle Clarke (16 December 1833-6 January 1898) served as a lieutenant colonel in the 30th Virginia Infantry Battalion. After the war, he lived in Baltimore, Maryland. He married Martha May Clark (23 August 1834-29 January 1867) and they had 1 child. Powhatan Clarke (1837-1917) became a doctor, moved to Louisiana, and also served in the Civil War. After the war, he practiced medicine in Baltimore. He married Louise F. Boyce (1839-1900) of Louisiana. Many of the Clarke family members are buried in Hollywood Cemetery in Richmond.
Scope and Content Information
Papers, 1854-1890, of the Clarke family of Gloucester County and Richmond, Virginia, consisting mainly of personal correspondence between Colin Clarke (1792-1865) of Gloucester County and Maxwell Troax Clarke (1830-1911) of Richmond, Virginia, discussing business and personal matters. Most of the correspondence discusses conditions in Gloucester County during the Civil War, especially the departure of slaves and the hardships of military occupation. The collection also includes correspondence to and from Mary Goode Lyle Clarke (1801-1884), Colin Douglas Clarke (1832-1862), Elizabeth Berkeley Cooke Clarke (1833-1906), Powhatan Clarke (1837-1917), Ellen Scott Clarke (1830-1908), and Sally Bland Clarke Manning (b. 1828). The collection also includes Maxwell T. Clarke's Civil War reminiscences, genealogical notes of the Clarke family, recipes, memorandums, certificates, commissions, oaths, military records, drafts, powers of attorney, receipts, lists, and accounts.
Located in oversize.
Contents List
- Letter. Colin Clarke, Gloucester, to Maxwell T. Clarke, n.p., 1 August 1854., 2 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. Colin Clarke, Gloucester, to Maxwell T. Clarke, Richmond, 6 September 1854., 4 p. (3 prints)
- Letter. Colin Clarke, Gloucester, to Maxwell T. Clarke, n.p., 20 September 1854., 4 p. (3 prints)
- Letter. Colin Clarke, Gloucester, to Maxwell T. Clarke, n.p., 22 September 1854., 4 p. (3 prints)
- Order. [S?] Barron, Office of Orders and Detail, Confederate States Navy Department, Richmond, to Privates J. H. Ellison, M. S. Clark and J. H. Anderson, 16 July 1861., 1 p. (1 print) (3 copies)
- Certification by Michal Graham, Quarter Master, C.S.A., 29 (July?) 1861., 1 p. (1 print)
- Receipt. William Payne, Culpeper, to Mrs. Clarke, 9 September [18]61., 1 p. (1 print)
- Receipt. W. T. Taliaferro, Manassas Junction, to Captain C. D. Clarke, 19 September 1861., 1 p. (1 print)
- Receipt. N. M. Cartmill, Winchester, to Messrs. Clarke and [Dallen?], 19 October 1861., 1 p. (1 print)
- Letter. John [?], Office of Provisions and Clothing, Confederate States Navy Department, Richmond, to Lieutenant Commander C. C. Simms, Steamer "Richmond", Fredericksburg, 24 October 1861., 1 p. (1 print)
- Receipt, [?] to H. C. Dallam, 25 October 1861, and Captain C. D. Clarke, 24 October 1861., 1 p. (1 print)
- Receipt. Wilmer McLean, Manassas, to Captain Clark, 2 January 1862., 1 p. (1 print)
- Transportation order for Captain Clark by Captain D. H. Wood, Transportation Office, C.S.A., Richmond, 6 January 1862., 1 p. (1 print)
- Descriptive list and account of pay and clothing of J. H. Anderson and M. T. Clarke, Company F, 20th Regiment of Virginia Volunteers, by Captain R. H. Cunningham, 19 January 1862., 1 p. (1 print)
- Account. Colin Clarke, Gloucester County, with Maxwell T. Clarke, October 1861 - March 1862., 1 p. (1 print)
- Appointment. Maxwell T. Clarke as acting master, by S. R. Mallory, Secretary of the Navy, C.S.A., Richmond 31 March 1862., 1 p. (1 print)
- Order. F. Forrest, Office of Orders and Detail, Confederate States Navy Department, Richmond, to M. T. Clarke, 14 May [18]62., 1 p. (1 print)
- Order. F. Forrest, Office of Orders and Detail, Confederate States Navy Department, Richmond, to M. T. Clarke, 16 May [18]62., 1 p. (1 print)
- Letter. Colin Clarke, Gloucester, to Maxwell T. Clarke, Richmond, 5 May 1862., 2 p. (3 prints)
- Letter. [?], Gloucester, to Maxwell T. Clarke, Richmond, 10 May 1862., 4 p. (3 prints) Mutilated.
- Receipts. S. B. [Cary?], to Miss A. Swann, for account, March - June 1862., 1 p. (1 print)
- Letter. [Colin Clarke?], Gloucester, to Maxwell T. Clarke, n.p., 20 July 1862., 4 p. (3 prints) Incomplete.
- Letter. Colin Clarke, Gloucester, to Maxwell T. Clarke, Richmond, 22 July 1862., 2 p. (3 prints)
- Letter. Colin Clarke, Gloucester, to Maxwell T. Clarke, n.p., 22 July 1862., 7 p. (5 prints)
- Letter. Sally Bland Manning, to [Maxwell T. Clarke], n.p., 8 August 1862., 4 p. (4 prints)
- Letter. Colin Clarke, Hickory Fork, to Maxwell T. Clarke, n.p., 9 August [1862]., 2 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. Colin Clarke, Gloucester, to Maxwell T. Clarke, n.p., 10 August 1862., 3 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. Colin Clarke, Gloucester, to Maxwell T. Clarke, n.p., 16 August 1862., 5 p. (5 prints)
- Letter. Maxwell T. Clarke, Richmond, to Powhatan Clarke, Alexandria, Louisiana, 17 August [18]62., 2 p. (3 prints)
- Letter. Colin Clarke, Gloucester, to [?], 31 August 1862., 6 p. (5 prints)
- Letter. Colin Clarke, Gloucester, to Maxwell T. Clarke, Richmond, 24 August 1862., 8 p. (7 prints)
- Letter. [Colin Clarke], Gloucester, to Maxwell T. Clarke, n.p., 7 September 1862., 4 p. (3 prints) Incomplete.
- Letter. Colin Clarke, Gloucester, to Maxwell T. Clarke, Richmond, 14 September 1862., 3 p. (3 prints)
- Letter. Colin Clarke, Gloucester, to Maxwell T. Clarke, Richmond, 16 September 1862., 3 p. (3 prints)
- Letter. Colin Clarke, Gloucester, to Maxwell T. Clarke, n.p., 5 May 1863., 6 p. (5 prints)
- Letter. Colin Clarke, Gloucester, to Maxwell T. Clarke and Ellen [Clarke], n.p., 21 May 1863., 4 p. (3 prints)
- Appointment. Maxwell T. Clarke as lieutenant, by S. R. Mallory, Secretary of the Navy, C.S.A., Richmond 25 May 1863., 1 p. (1 print)
- Letter. Colin Clarke, Gloucester, to Maxwell T. Clarke, n.p., [15?] June 1863., 4 p. (3 prints)
- Letter. Colin Clarke, Gloucester, to Maxwell T. Clarke, Richmond, 23 June 1863., 4 p. (4 prints)
- Letter. Colin Clarke, Gloucester, to Maxwell T. Clarke, n.p., 16 July 1863., 4 p. (3 prints)
- Letter. Colin Clarke, Gloucester, to Maxwell T. Clarke, Richmond, 26 July 1863., 4 p. (4 prints)
- Power of attorney. Colin Clarke, Gloucester County, to Maxwell T. Clarke, Richmond, 27 July 1863., 1 p. (1 print)
- Letter. Colin Clarke, Gloucester, to Maxwell T. Clarke, Richmond, 2 August 1863., 2 p. (3 prints)
- Letter. Colin Clarke, Gloucester, to Maxwell T. Clarke, Richmond, 23 August 1863., 4 p. (4 prints)
- Letter. Colin Clarke, Gloucester, to Maxwell t. Clarke, n.p., 20 September 1863., 4 p. (3 prints)
- Letter. Colin Clarke, Gloucester, to Maxwell T. Clarke and Ellen [Clarke], [Richmond], 24 September 1863., 4 p. (3 prints)
- Draft. Colin Clarke, n.p., on Maxwell T. Clarke, Richmond, 21 November 1863., 1 p. (1 print)
- Letter. Colin Clarke, Gloucester, to Maxwell T. Clarke, Richmond, 7 Demember 1863., 4 p. (4 prints) Incomplete.
- Letter. Colin Clarke, Gloucester, to Maxwell T. CLarke, Richmond, 29 December 1863., 4 p. (5 prints)
- Appointment. Maxwell T. Clarke as lieutenant, by S. R. Mallory, Secretary of the Navy, C.S.A., Richmond 7 January 1864., 1 p. (1 print)
- Letter. [Mrs. Colin Clarke], Warner Hall, to Maxwell T. Clarke, n.p., 16 January 1864., 8 p. (6 prints)
- Letter. Colin Clarke, Gloucester, to Maxwell T. Clarke, n.p., 2 February 1864., 6 p. (5 prints)
- Appointment. Maxwell T. CLarke as first lieutenant, by S. R. Mallory, Secretary of the Navy, C.S.A., Richmond 2 June 1864., 1 p. (1 print)
- Order. [T. S. Lee?], Office of Orders and Detail, Confederate States Navy Department, Danville, to Maxwell T. Clarke, 10 April 1865., 1 p. (1 print)
- Parole issued Maxwell T. Clarke, First Lieutenant, Confederate States Navy, Greensboro, North Carolina, 1 May 1865., 1 p. (1 print)
- Oath of allegiance to United States, by Maxwell T. Clarke, Richmond, 31 May 1865., 1 p. (1 print)
- Commission. Maxwell T. Clarke, as captain of Company F, First Regiment Virginia Infantry, by Gilbert C. Walter, Governor, 20 May 1872., 1 p. (1 print)
- Certificate of election of Maxwell T. Clarke as justice of the peace, Richmond, by Andrew Jinkins, Clerk, 27 May 1872., 1 p. (1 print)
- Certificate of election of Maxwell T. Clarke as justice of the peace, Richmond, by Andrew Jinkins, Clerk, 25 May 1878., 1 p. (1 print)
- Letter. Maxwell T. Clarke, Richmond, to [?], 25 October 1890., 6 p. (6 prints)
- Letter. Betty B. Clarke, n.p., to Maxwell T. Clarke, Richmond, 4 June [?]., 3 p. (3 prints)
- Letter. [Mrs. Colin Clarke], Warner Hall, to Maxwell T. Clarke, Richmond, n.p., August [?]., 4 p. (3 prints)
- Letter. [Mrs. Colin Clarke], n.p., to Maxwell T. Clarke, n.p., n.d., 2 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. [Mrs. Colin Clarke], n.p., to Maxwell T. Clarke, Richmond, n.d., 1 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. Colin Clarke, n.p., to Powhatan R. Page, Maxwell T. Clarke, James A. Scott, or George Lee, n.p., n.d., 2 p. (3 prints)
- Memorandum concerning contents of certain boxes, n.d., 1 p. (1 print)
- Memorandum by Colin Clarke concerning supplies, n.d., 2 p. (2 prints)
- Clarke family genealogical chart., 1 p. (1 print)
- Goode-Clarke-Bland Family genealogical notes., 7 p. (7 prints)
- Recipe given by Mrs. Martha Page to Mrs. Colin Clarke., 2 p. (2 prints)